<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: R | Creative morphometrics]]></title>
  <link href="http://paulidealiste.github.io/blog/categories/r/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://paulidealiste.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-02T14:35:02+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://paulidealiste.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Miloš Blagojević]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PLS Model for Temperature in R]]></title>
    <link href="http://paulidealiste.github.io/blog/2014/09/02/pls-model-for-temperature-in-r/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-02T13:01:59+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://paulidealiste.github.io/blog/2014/09/02/pls-model-for-temperature-in-r</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing on the post about the climate data extraction in R, this post demonstrates a simple approach to using PLS (partial least squares) for determining the common covariance patterns between morphology and mean monthly temperature (although the model is likely to be bad). Morphology data can be found  <a href = "http://goo.gl/7BQ4tT"> here</a>. This dataset only contains PCA scores of individuals for the first two PC axes (Figure 1), extracted from the Fourier descriptors of horn shape. PC1 axis (92%) clearly separates males and females on the basis of respective horn shape.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/pca1plot.png" width="450" height="393" title="&lsquo;ordinary PCA&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Temperature data are extracted using geoTiffs from  <a href="http://www.worldclim.org/" target="_blank">WorldClim</a> database, as in the mentioned post about climate data extraction. The ready-made dataset of mean monthly temperatures for the above study locality can be found <a href = "http://goo.gl/2fAlAF"> here</a>.</p>

<p>```r Importing data and plotting the Figure 1 PCA
fourierPC &lt;&ndash; read.table(&ldquo;~/fourierPC.txt&rdquo;, header = TRUE, sep = &ldquo;,&rdquo;) #by default they are in the home directory
matTaraMean &lt;&ndash; read.table(&ldquo;~/matTaraMean.txt&rdquo;, header = TRUE, sep = &ldquo;,&rdquo;)</p>

<p>library(ggplot2)
theme_set(theme_bw())
sex &lt;&ndash; c(&ldquo;f&rdquo;,&ldquo;f&rdquo;,&ldquo;m&rdquo;,&ldquo;m&rdquo;,&ldquo;f&rdquo;, &ldquo;m&rdquo;,&ldquo;m&rdquo;,&ldquo;m&rdquo;,&ldquo;f&rdquo;,&ldquo;m&rdquo;,&ldquo;f&rdquo;,&ldquo;f&rdquo;,&ldquo;m&rdquo;,&ldquo;f&rdquo;,&ldquo;f&rdquo;,&ldquo;m&rdquo;,&ldquo;f&rdquo;,&ldquo;f&rdquo;,&ldquo;f&rdquo;,&ldquo;m&rdquo;,&ldquo;f&rdquo;,&ldquo;m&rdquo;,&ldquo;f&rdquo;,&ldquo;f&rdquo;,&ldquo;m&rdquo;,&ldquo;f&rdquo;) #individual sex is known in advance
ggplot(fourierPC, aes(PC1, PC2)) + geom_point(size = 5, shape = 19, aes(color = sex))
```
PLS analysis is a useful multivariate technique used for determining the common variation patterns in two blocks of data and is sometimes reffered to as PLS regression. In this post, of all PLS implementations in R, the choice is on the fabulous <em>plsdepot</em> library, developed and maintained by Gaston Sanchez, whose <a href="http://gastonsanchez.com" target="_blank"> blog/personal page</a> and work in general was a great insipiration for Creative Morphometrics. His approach is very well explained and documented over at his page, so only direct implementation on the data above will be provided here.</p>

<p><code>r PLS plsdepot library
library(plsdepot)
taraMat &lt;- matTaraMean[sample(221, 26),] #extract 26 samples from 221 raster grid values
climatePLS &lt;- plsreg1(taraMat, fourierPC$PC1, comps = 3)
plot(climatePLS)#plot circle of correlations in order to determine the influence of predictor variables
</code></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/RplotCircles.png" width="450" height="393" title="&lsquo;PLS correlation circle&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>It is obvious from Figure 2. that the variables in question share no common variation pattern and are totally unrelated. If the chosen data was better, some of the blue lines (predictors) would run parallel with the orange one (response). If the R<sup>2</sup> value for this model is examined (it is a part of climatePLS object &ndash; climatePLS$R2) the unrelatedness of predictors and response in this model gets even more obvious (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.035). Predictors in this model are also highly correlated within themselves, which renders them rather useles in prediction, as was stated at the onset.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simple Angles and Nice Plots]]></title>
    <link href="http://paulidealiste.github.io/blog/2014/06/09/simple-angles-and-nice-plots/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-09T17:28:06+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://paulidealiste.github.io/blog/2014/06/09/simple-angles-and-nice-plots</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Angles were important for some of the most interesting research in morphometrics. The approach of Rao and Suryawanshi, 1998<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. introduced the angles within the landmark triangulation grids as an alternative to Procrustes superimposition for extracting shape data. This post does not perform the procedures described by Rao (which are ported to R in &ldquo;Geometric morphometrics in R&rdquo; by J.Claude, 2008), but instead aims at extracting angle data, from configurations of landmarks, after Procrustes superimposition. The code presented here is motivated by the <em>polarRotator</em> function from some of the previous pyhton-related posts, and it presents landmark data as polar angles. These angles represent the angular deviation of each landmark from the centroid of the respective configuration (Figure 1), so that the variability in their position with respect to xy centroid coordinates, may represent their shape differences. Since superimposition procedure sets all configurations centroids to the origin, they are all 0,0. Dataset used is the same as for the triangulation post.</p>

<p>```r Plotting the circle, centroid axes and mean configuration
library(geomorph)
library(ggplot2)
library(reshape2)
library(plyr)
theme_set(theme_bw())</p>

<p>load(&ldquo;capSample.RData&rdquo;)</p>

<p>capGPA &lt;&ndash; gpagen(capSample)
capCoords &lt;&ndash; capGPA$coords
mshapeCap &lt;&ndash; mshape(capCoords) #mean configuration is great for illustrations
capCentro &lt;&ndash; capGPA$Csize</p>

<p>circleFun &lt;&ndash; function(center = c(0,0), npoints = 100) #drawing an enlosing circle set at the origin (0,0)
{
  r = 0.5
  tt &lt;&ndash; seq(0,2*pi,length.out = npoints)
  xx &lt;&ndash; center[1] + r * cos(tt)
  yy &lt;&ndash; center[2] + r * sin(tt)
  return(data.frame(x = xx, y = yy))
}</p>

<p>enclosing &lt;&ndash; circleFun(npoints = 100) #it should be centered at zero and have diameter 0.5
ggCirc &lt;&ndash; ggplot(enclosing, aes(x=x,y=y)) + geom_path(size = 1, color = &ldquo;darkgrey&rdquo;, linetype = 1)
ggCirc &lt;&ndash; ggCirc + geom_hline(size = 1, color = &ldquo;darkgrey&rdquo;, linetype = 1) + geom_vline(size = 1, color = &ldquo;darkgrey&rdquo;, linetype = 1)</p>

<p>linesAng &lt;&ndash; data.frame(x1 = c(0, 0, 0, 0), y1 = c(0, 0, 0, 0), x2 = mshapeCap[,1], y2 = mshapeCap[,2]) #point coordinates
linesAng &lt;&ndash; data.frame(linesAng, x3 = linesAng$x2 * 20, y3 = linesAng$y2 *20) #so that the lines would extend through landmarks</p>

<p>ggCirc &lt;&ndash; ggCirc + geom_segment(data = linesAng, aes(x = x1, y = y1, xend = x3, yend = y3), colour = &ldquo;lightblue&rdquo;, size = 1)
ggCirc &lt;&ndash; ggCirc + geom_point(size = 4.2, color = &ldquo;orange&rdquo;, data = data.frame(mshapeCap), aes(x=X1, y = X2))
ggCirc &lt;&ndash; ggCirc + geom_text(data = data.frame(mshapeCap), aes(x=X1, y = X2, label = c(1:16)), vjust = -1.2)
ggCirc &lt;&ndash; ggCirc + coord_cartesian(xlim= c(-0.55, 0.55), ylim= c(-0.55, 0.55))
``` <br/>
<img class="center" src="/images/AnglesLandmarks.png" width="500" height="478" title="&lsquo;Landmarks polar angles&rsquo;" ></p>

<p><em>ggplot2</em> has one great geom, polar_angle() that will transform any shape, from Cartesian to polar coordinates. Unfortunately it does not give polar angles as well, but the plot is informative (Figure 2), since landmarks are ordered according to their angular deviation from 0, i.e. the X and Y axes defining the 0.5 centroid-centered ellipse.</p>

<p><code>r Polar coordinate system in ggplot2
ggPolar &lt;- ggplot(data.frame(mshapeCap), aes(x=X1, y=X2)) + geom_point(size = 4.2, color = "orange")
ggPolar &lt;- ggPolar + geom_text(aes(label = c(1:16)), vjust = 1.5)
ggPolar &lt;- ggPolar + coord_polar(start = 0) + xlab("x") + ylab("y")
</code></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/AnglesPolar.png" width="500" height="436" title="&lsquo;Landmarks polar coordinate system&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Polar angles can be calculated by using the atan2 (arctangent) function, which takes two parameters, x and y and gives one point estimate of the polar angle in radians. This number is really the angle between the positive x-axis of a plane (X from Figure 1) and the point given by its xy coordinates. Since after superimposition the x-axis lies at zero for all landmark configurations, it would be sufficent to use only xy coodinates of landmarks, since centroids are also at 0.</p>

<p>```r Polar angles with atan2 function
polarAngler &lt;&ndash; function(A) #function to calculate polar angles from the array
{
  siz &lt;&ndash; dim(A)[3]
  len &lt;&ndash; dim(A)[1]
  polarAngles &lt;&ndash; vector(&ldquo;list&rdquo;, siz)
  for (i in 1:siz)
  {</p>

<pre><code>temp &lt;- atan2(A[,2,i], A[,1,i])
polarAngles[[i]] &lt;- temp
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  polarAngles &lt;&ndash; array(unlist(polarAngles), dim = c(len,1,siz))
  return(polarAngles)
}</p>

<p>library(circular)
library(colortools)</p>

<p>pAngles &lt;&ndash; polarAngler(capCoords) #angles for all configurations
mAngles &lt;&ndash; apply(pAngles, 1, mean) #mean angles for each landmark
col1 &lt;&ndash; pals(&ldquo;fish&rdquo;) #paletes from colortools
col2 &lt;&ndash; pals(&ldquo;ocean&rdquo;)
col3 &lt;&ndash; pals(&ldquo;mystery&rdquo;)
colorPoint &lt;&ndash; c(col1, col2, col3, &ldquo;#9A76F5&rdquo;) #16 colors for landmarks in whell</p>

<p>plot.circular(circular(t(mAngles), type = &ldquo;angles&rdquo;), sep = 0.0003, col = colorPoint, cex = 1.5)
legend(0.3,0.6, legend = 1:16, fill = colorPoint, cex = 0.7)</p>

<p>```</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/AnglesMean.png" width="500" height="436" title="&lsquo;Landmarks ordered by angles&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Figure 3 shows the distribution of landmarks from along a circular path (0,     π). It is obvious that landmarks form two distinct groups, one above, and one below the x-axis, with the exception of landmarks 7, 8 and 10 which are the most parallel to the x-axis. The proportion of the overall shape variability left in these angles must be thouroghly checked, but it is not easy, since angle-data can not be analysed by conventional statistics, but by circular or compositional methods. R provides some libraries for this, <em>circular</em> and <em>CircStats</em> which are both derived from the book of Jammalamadaka and Sengupta, &ldquo;Topics in circular Statistics&rdquo; from 2001. If one more individual is added to the circle-plot (Figure 3) it can be can visually inspected how much its coordinates (landmark polar angles) deviate from the sample mean (Figure 4).</p>

<p><code>r Adding individual 10 to circular plot
ce &lt;- circular(rbind(t(mAngles), pAngles[,,10])) #deviation of individual 10 from the mean
plot.circular(ce, sep = 0.0003, col = colorPoint, cex = 1.5)
legend(0.3,0.6, legend = 1:16, fill = colorPoint, cex = 0.7)
</code></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/AnglesMean2.png" width="500" height="436" title="&lsquo;Landmarks ordered by angles + 10&rsquo;" ></p>

<p> Some variablity is present around landmarks 10, 6 and 5, while others are nearly or completely overlapping. The variability may not be large, but it will be checked in future posts, as well as possible PCA with the angular data.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Rao C.R. and S. Suryawanshi. 1998. Statistical analysis of shape of objects based on landmark data. <em>PNAS</em> <strong>93</strong>: 12132-12136.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modularity, Graphs and Triangulations]]></title>
    <link href="http://paulidealiste.github.io/blog/2014/05/03/modularity-graphs-and-triangulations/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-03T00:08:25+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://paulidealiste.github.io/blog/2014/05/03/modularity-graphs-and-triangulations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing on the previous post, procedures presented here show the comparison between the usual assesment of modularity in the collection of landmarks (same dataset as before) and the depiction of modular structure through graph theory. Usually, modularity in the mammalian cranium is determined a-priori, according to some of the established hypotheses about the developmental origin of cranial elements. One of the most prevalent hypotheses is the two-module organization, one module comprising of elements originating mainly from the neural crest embryonic tissue (anterior cranium) and one comprising of elements with somitomeric origin (posterior cranium). Following code shows the test of this specific hypothesis using <em>geomorph</em> package functions, and additional usage of <em>deldir</em> for visualization of modularity hypotheses.</p>

<p>```r Importing data, basic GM, modularity and plots
library(geomorph)
library(deldir)
library(ggplot2)
load(&ldquo;capSample.RData&rdquo;)
theme_set(theme_bw())</p>

<p>capGPA &lt;&ndash; gpagen(capSample)
capCoords &lt;&ndash; capGPA$coords
mshapeCap &lt;&ndash; mshape(capCoords) #mean shape is useful for plotting</p>

<h1>vector depicting the division of landmarks according to modularity</h1>

<p>modularity1.gps &lt;&ndash; c(&ldquo;A&rdquo;,&ldquo;A&rdquo;,&ldquo;A&rdquo;,&ldquo;A&rdquo;,&ldquo;A&rdquo;,&ldquo;A&rdquo;,&ldquo;A&rdquo;,&ldquo;A&rdquo;,&ldquo;B&rdquo;,&ldquo;B&rdquo;,&ldquo;A&rdquo;,&ldquo;B&rdquo;,&ldquo;B&rdquo;,&ldquo;B&rdquo;,&ldquo;B&rdquo;,&ldquo;B&rdquo;)</p>

<h1>test for modularity based on the RV coefficient</h1>

<p>modularity1 &lt;&ndash; compare.modular.partitions(capCoords, landgroups = modularity1.gps)</p>

<h1>plot of landmark membership to a-priori modules</h1>

<p>deldir(mshapeCap[,1], mshapeCap[,2], plotit = TRUE, wlines = &ldquo;triang&rdquo;, xlim = c(-0.2,0.55))
points(mshapeCap[c(1:8,11),1], mshapeCap[c(1:8,11),2], col = &ldquo;#FF8740&rdquo;, pch = 19, cex = 1.2)
points(mshapeCap[c(9,10,12:16),1], mshapeCap[c(9,10,12:16),2], col = &ldquo;#61B4CF&rdquo;, pch = 19, cex = 1.2)
legend(0.2,0.4, legend = c(&ldquo;neural crest&rdquo;, &ldquo;somitomere&rdquo;), fill = colormap)
```</p>

<p>Figure 1 shows the theoretical distribution of the RV coefficients, calculated for all posible two-module subdivisions of landmarks, as well as the observed RV value from the hypothesis depicted in Figure 2. Since the observed value is lower than most of the hypothetic values, then it could be said that this modularity hypothesis stands.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/RVmodularity.png" width="570" height="497" title="&lsquo;RV coefficients&rsquo;" >
<img class="center" src="/images/modularityLand.png" width="344" height="376" title="&lsquo;Modularity hypothesis&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>The idea for using graph theory representation and analysis of modularity is based on correlation matrix, same one from the previous post. Correlation matrix was obtained through Delaunay triangulation and every vertex (node) in the graph actually represents the 1/3 of the total area of all Delaunay triangles emanating from the corresponding landmark.</p>

<p><code>r Delaunay triangulation and derivation of the correlation matrix
cicoCap &lt;- t(apply(capCoords, 3, function(A) deldir(A[,1],A[,2])$summary[,4]))
cicoCap &lt;- data.frame(cicoCap)
names(cicoCap) &lt;- paste("lm", c(1:16), sep = "")
capCor &lt;- abs(cor(cicoCap)) #correlation matrix
diag(capCor) &lt;- 0 #diagonals must be set to zero
</code></p>

<p>Graph based on the correlation matrix can be created and manipulated with the wonderful <em>igraph</em> package. Vertices of this graph will be abovementioned areas, while the edges will represent correlation (edge weights) between areas around each landmark. According to weights, edges can be colored and the strength of thier lines increased, so that the most correlated landmarks wolud be more obvious.</p>

<p><code>r iGraph graph creation and manipulation
graph &lt;- graph.adjacency(capCor, weighted=TRUE, mode="upper")
E(graph)[ weight &gt; 0.5 ]$color &lt;- "#A63E00"
E(graph)[ weight &gt; 0.5 ]$width &lt;- 3.6
E(graph)[ weight &gt; -0.5 &amp; weight &lt; 0.5 ]$color &lt;- "#D6EBFF"
E(graph)[ weight &gt; -0.5 &amp; weight &lt; 0.5 ]$width &lt;- 1.2
</code></p>

<p>Modularity, or community structure in the graph theory represents the degree of compartmentalization in the graph structure, based on the spatial relationship or the weights of graph edges. Although, a-priori subdivision of graph vertices is possible, and the evaluation of such graph community can be easily done, the advantage of graph theory for modularity is the availability of algorithms for searching the community structure, so it can derive subdivsion a-posteriori, that can be compared to the hypothesis from Figure 1.</p>

<p>```r Graph modularity and plotting
gsc &lt;&ndash; leading.eigenvector.community(graph, weights = E(graph)$weights)
modularity(graph, membership(gsc))
colormap &lt;&ndash; c(&ldquo;#FF8740&rdquo;, &ldquo;#61B4CF&rdquo;)
V(graph)$color &lt;&ndash; colormap[gsc$membership] #color graph vertices according to community</p>

<h1>graph layout will be circular since values for the edges range from 0.2 to 0.9,</h1>

<h1>and they all form similar attractive force between the vertices.</h1>

<p>graph$layout &lt;&ndash; layout.fruchterman.reingold #really no effect on the shape of this graph</p>

<p>plot(graph, vertex.size = 20, vertex.shape = &ldquo;circle&rdquo;)
legend(0.8,1.4, legend = c(&ldquo;neural crest&rdquo;, &ldquo;somitomere&rdquo;), fill = colormap)
```</p>

<p>Leading eigenvector community algorithm tries to find community structure in the graph by calculating the eigenvector of the modularity matrix for the largest positive eigenvalue and then separating vertices into two communities based on the sign of the corresponding element in the eigenvector (Newman, 2006<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>). This method was preffered over many others because it is closer to usual multivariate methods, such as PCA, that are commonly used to depict variability patterns.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/modularityGraph.png" width="541" height="467" title="&lsquo;Modularity graph&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Graph community strucure depicts modularity in the landmark configurations accurately, with the exception of lm16, that is positioned on the posterior basicranium. Higher correlations are, on average, present within modules while between modules, only one connection is higher than 0.5, that between lm2 and lm14. Since these landmarks lay on the opposite sides of the cranium, they may encompass the variability in total anterior-posterior length. i.e. cranial size.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Newman, M.E.J. 2006. Modularity and community structure in networks. <em>PNAS</em> <strong>103</strong>: 8577-8582.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Delaunay Triangulation Experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://paulidealiste.github.io/blog/2014/04/04/delaunay-triangulation-for-modularity-pt-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-04T18:09:37+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://paulidealiste.github.io/blog/2014/04/04/delaunay-triangulation-for-modularity-pt-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since landmark data consists of x and y Cartesian coordinates, it would be useful if they could be represented by one summary number, that would preserve the spatial information. This is just a proposal of one possiblity using Delaunay triangulation between landmark configurations, and the average area of all triangles emanating from individual landmarks. Since landmark position within the triangulation grid would influence the shape and size as well as number of triangles around it, the area should preserve enoguh information about the spatial relationships of landmarks. Dataset for this post consists of ventral aspect half configurations from <a href="http://goo.gl/LP3xsd" target="_blank">here</a>. Delaunay triangulation will be performed using <em>deldir</em> R package, since it reports the mentioned triangle areas as a part of object summary.</p>

<p>```r Importing data, basic GM, calculating the triangulation, extracting areas and plotting
library(deldir)
library(geomorph)
load(&ldquo;capSample.RData&rdquo;)</p>

<p>capreolusGPA &lt;&ndash; gpagen(capSample)
capGPAcoords &lt;&ndash; capreolusGPA$coords</p>

<p>delCap &lt;&ndash; deldir(capSample[,,10][,1], capSample[,,10][,2]) #extract any individual from an array for visualization
plot(delCap, col=c(&ldquo;lightblue&rdquo;,&ldquo;lightgrey&rdquo;,1,1,1), lwd = c(2,2), xlim = c(150, 400), cex = 0.1, ann = FALSE)
points(capSample[,,10], col = &ldquo;orange&rdquo;, pch = 16, cex = 1.4)
text(capSample[,,10], label = c(1:16), pos = 3, ceo = 0.5)</p>

<p>areaCap &lt;&ndash; t(apply(capGPAcoords, 3, function(A) deldir(A[,1],A[,2])$summary[,4])) #calcuate areas per landmark
areaCap &lt;&ndash; data.frame(areaCap)
names(areaCap) &lt;&ndash; paste(&ldquo;lm&rdquo;, c(1:16), sep = &ldquo;&rdquo;)
```</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/Delaunay.png" width="401" height="473" title="&lsquo;Delaunay&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Values in the areaCap matrix represent average areas of all triangles emanating from the landmark in question, so its dimensions are 60x16. Correlation matrix (16x16) can be calculated from the areaCap matrix, and it should reflect relative positioning of landmarks through spatial grouping pattern. This can be checked visually using <em>corrplot</em> package visualization of the correlation matrix, which allows direct assesment of emerging patterns in the matrix. Additionally, this package allows reordering of rows and columns according to hierarchical clustering algorhithms and representing the desired number of clusters with rectangles in the correlation plot. This can only be considered as an idea of general modularity, since landmarks from the same cranial region should be correlated more than distant landmarks. But the transformation of xy coordinates to average triangle areas may have introduced non-biological variation or obscured some of the natural variation and these procedures as well as subsequent analyses may be treated only as a fun experiment and visualization tool for now.</p>

<p><code>r Drawing correlation plot
library(corrplot)
capCor &lt;- cor(areaCap)
corrplot(capCor, method = "circle", tl.cex = 0.93, order = "hclust", addrect = 3)
</code></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/Corrplot.png" width="570" height="529" title="&lsquo;Delaunay&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Correlation plot with three proposed general landmark groups in the matrix reveals that the correlations are, on average, higher for locally grouped landmaks, especially the anterior ones, from 1 to 7. This can`t be used as a reliablie test for modularity hypothesis, but it can serve as a basis for further analyses based on construcing linked graphs or networks using correlation matrices from landmark data, where the xy coordinates are transformed to one number. Also this can be a useful way of representing modular structure visually, since both Delaunay and correlation plots are highly customizable, and can be colored according to real modularity hypotheses. Testing some of these will be the subject of future posts.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Extracting Climate Data in R]]></title>
    <link href="http://paulidealiste.github.io/blog/2014/03/27/extracting-climate-data-in-r/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-27T19:44:55+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://paulidealiste.github.io/blog/2014/03/27/extracting-climate-data-in-r</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With the ongoing expand of the available geospatial databases in raster format (GeoTiff) it is getting easier to analyse the relationship between any complex morphology, captured in landmark data, and i.e. climate or precipitation data with the help of partial least squares (PLS). R has a wonderful <em>raser</em>, <em>sp</em> and <em>gdal</em> packages that facilitate the extraction of the geospatial data from GeoTiff raster grids. In this post the geoTiff used will be from the <a href="http://www.worldclim.org/" target="_blank">WorldClim</a> website, and the climate data for European square 16, where some of my real samples originate from. In order to get this data you can follow the downloads section of the WorldClim website and choose download data by tile, 30 arc-seconds resolution. When a map opens the dataset for this post would be under the map, when clicked on the square zone 16 and finally download the Mean Temperature. This is a .zip file with twelve GeoTiffs, one for each month. Unpack the files in a pre-destined directory, and declare this a working directory in the R session.
<code>r Importing libraries, reading and inital plots of the GeoTiff data
setwd("~/tmean") #this is the folder with all the GeoTiffs
library(raster)
library(sp)
library(rgdal)
meanJan &lt;- raster("tmean1_16.tif") #mean temp for January etc.
meanFeb &lt;- raster("tmean2_16.tif")
meanMar &lt;- raster("tmean3_16.tif")
meanApr &lt;- raster("tmean4_16.tif")
meanMaj &lt;- raster("tmean5_16.tif")
meanJun &lt;- raster("tmean6_16.tif")
meanJul &lt;- raster("tmean7_16.tif")
meanAvg &lt;- raster("tmean8_16.tif")
meanSep &lt;- raster("tmean9_16.tif")
meanOkt &lt;- raster("tmean10_16.tif")
meanNov &lt;- raster("tmean11_16.tif")
meanDec &lt;- raster("tmean12_16.tif")
plot(meanJan) #will simply get the basic R plot of a GeoTiff raster
</code>
<img class="center" src="/images/meanJan.png" width="521" height="410" title="&lsquo;mean january&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>After reading in the basic data, <em>raster</em> package offers several formats in which to keep the data, besides the basic raster. The most useful one is a raster stack which really is just the piled-up rasters that can be manipulated together. Also one useful visual help is the addition of the country boundaries followed by zooming in to the extent of the country or region where the samples originate from. Country boundaries .shp files is freely avalilable from <a href="http://thematicmapping.org/downloads/world_borders.php" target="_blank">thematicmapping</a>. When downloaded they should be in the same directory as the GeoTiffs.</p>

<p>```r Creating the raster stack, adding boundaries and zooming to an extent
mtStack &lt;&ndash; stack(meanJan, meanFeb, meanMar, meanApr, meanMaj, meanJun, meanJul, meanAvg, meanSep, meanOkt, meanNov, meanDec)
bounds &lt;&ndash; readOGR(dsn=getwd(), layer= &ldquo;TM_WORLD_BORDERS-0.3&rdquo;) #import borders
plot(meanJan) #plot the raster file for any month
extentR &lt;&ndash; drawExtent()</p>

<h1>drawExtent enters the interactive mode where you can draw the polygon for zooming based on two points, top right and lower left</h1>

<h1>values in extentR are coordinates in WGS84 datum and expressed as longitude data</h1>

<p>plot(zoom(bounds, extentR), add = TRUE)</p>

<h1>unfortunately this does not work well since it will plot the bounds in the zoom extent</h1>

<h1>and if the both raster and bounds are needed then it might be ok to overlap them in GIMP</h1>

<p>plot(zoom(meanJan, extentR), add = TRUE)
```
<img class="center" src="/images/zoomara.png" width="519" height="414" title="&lsquo;mean january zoomed&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Before final extraction of the climate data it can be useful to plot each month`s mean temperature for the selected extent of the rasater. This can be easily achieved by using the <em>rasterVis</em> package levelplot and the extentR variable, which can be used to cut through all raster layers in the stack.</p>

<p>```r Cutting the stack and drawing levelplot for all months
library(rasterVis)
cutStack &lt;&ndash; (crop(mtStack, extentR))/10</p>

<h1>division by 10 is needed since the temperature data in this GeoTiff is x10 for saving memory-important</h1>

<p>names(cutStack) &lt;&ndash; month.abb
levelplot(cutStack) #may take long time to plot
histogram(cutStack)
```
<img class="center" src="/images/meanLevel1.png" width="570" height="467" title="&lsquo;mean all&rsquo;" >
<img class="center" src="/images/meanLevel2.png" width="570" height="467" title="&lsquo;mean all h&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Slightly more efficient than the drawExtent is the spatialPolygons function from the <em>sp</em> package that will be used for definition of the real sampling localities, by simply drawing boundaries of the localities by hand or using the known positional data. It is best if approximate latitude/longitude coordinates are known in advance so that the defining polygon can be drawn connecting several corners-points, that form the broader sampling area border. If coordinates are not known in advance then the drawExtent should be used first for finding the latitude/longitude of the spatial polygon points, and then making the SpatialPolygon object out of them, as described next.</p>

<p>```r Extracting spatialPolygons by latitude/longitude pairs
taraCoord &lt;&ndash; rbind(c(19.241867, 44.012571), c(19.351730, 43.976511), c(19.518585, 43.923121), c(19.435501, 43.894924), c(19.317398, 43.896903), c(19.261780, 43.955259), c(19.241867, 44.012571))
R1Coord &lt;&ndash; rbind(c(24.656067, 45.627484), c(25.252075, 45.575600), c(25.628357, 45.525592), c(25.488281, 45.3000007), c(25.046082, 45.381080), c(24.672546, 45.539060), c(24.656067, 45.627484))</p>

<h1>these objects are matrices with two columns, one for latitude of a polygon corner and the other the longitude</h1>

<p>polyTara &lt;&ndash; SpatialPolygons(list(Polygons(list(Polygon(taraCoord)), 1))) #declare object type
polyR1 &lt;&ndash; SpatialPolygons(list(Polygons(list(Polygon(R1Coord)), 1)))
<code>``
After all spatial polygons are defined, final step involves the extraction of the mean temperature values from the points encircled by the polygon in question, for all months. Since GeoTiffs are raster formats, they are carrying the information on the temperature in the points of the bitmap grid, so if the polygon is too small, small will be the number of the grid-points inside, maybe smaller than the number of individuals. To avoid this make sampling area broader, and in this case polyTara has some 220 individual grid points inside, which means 220 values for the mean temperature in the area. If we have i.e. ten individuals per population it is necessery to have also 10 mean temperature values, so that both blocks in subsequent PLS would have same dimensionality. R</code>s basic sample function can be used to extract random values from the i.e. 220 points within the population (Tara and R1) polygons. This simulates random sampling of individuals from the sampling locality and after that any analysis can be done, from linear models to PLS, which will be shown in future posts.</p>

<p><code>r Extracting climate data and preparing the dataset according to the number of individuals
matTaraMean &lt;- extract(cutStack, polyTara)[[1]]
matR1Mean &lt;- extract(cutStack, polyR1)[[1]]
plot(cutStack$Jan)
plot(polyTara, add = TRUE)
plot(polyR1, add = TRUE)
n &lt;- dim(matTaraMean)[1] #for sampling convenience
m &lt;- dim(matR1Mean)[1]
taraMat &lt;- matTaraMean[sample(n, 10),] #this is the final extracted data
R1Mat &lt;- matR1Mean[sample(m, 10),]
library(ggplot2)
library(reshape2)
plotter &lt;- data.frame(rbind(taraMat, R1Mat), loc = c(rep("Ta",10), rep("R1", 10))) #for ggplot2
forplo &lt;- melt(plotter)
m &lt;- ggplot(forplo, aes(x = value, fill = loc)) + geom_histogram() + facet_grid(variable~.)
</code></p>

<p>Figure 5. shows the locations of tara and R1 spatial polygons within the zoomed extent of the zone 16, while in Figure 6. barplots are shown for 10 random points for all months, and for both localities, for comparison.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/Fig5climate.png" width="536" height="433" title="&lsquo;localities&rsquo;" >
<img class="center" src="/images/Fig6climate.png" width="802" height="700" title="&lsquo;histograms&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>It is obvious that the Tara locality has higer mean monthly temperature, on average for every month, and also it has less temperature variaton than R1.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
